-==www.RagBear.com==- 是, 首相  第1季第2集
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-=破烂熊字幕组=- 翻译: song123 校对&时间轴: tpring
电视讲话
汉弗莱爵士等着见您 首相
Sir Humphrey is waiting to see you, Prime Minister.
谢谢 伯纳 让他进来
Thank you, Bernard. Show him in.
是 首相
Yes, Prime Minister.
早上好 首相      啊 汉弗莱 早上好
Good morning, Prime Minister. Ah, Humphrey, good morning.
时差倒过来了没有?
How's the jet lag?
我没时差...抱歉 我觉得我的时差是反的
I find that jet lag affects me more going the other way.
我在白宫会面的时候感觉非常累
I felt frightfully tired at the White House.
都不记得他说过什么了
I can scarcely remember a thing he said.
他也没真的说多少 首相 他也很累
He didn't really say much, He was frightfully tired too.
真让人担心是吧?
Bit worrying, isn't it?
我们政治家总是满世界飞
Statesmen such as myself jetting all over the world,
出席关于人类未来的主要会议 我们都累晕了
attending conferences on the future and we're zonked?
有可能 首相
It would be, Prime Minister.
也许就因为这个 谈判总提前由我这种下属完成
Perhaps that's why negotiations are done in advance.
一般不留给晕了的人完成
They can hardly be left in the hands of the zonked.
您找我什么事呢?
Now, what did you want to see me about?
首相? 首相
Prime Minister? Prime Minister!
啊 是的 伯纳 啊 汉弗莱 早上好
Ah, yes, Bernard. Ah, Humphrey, good morning!
您想要见我的      哦 有吗?
You wanted to see me. Oh. Did I?
你不知道他要说什么吗?
Don't you know what it was about?
他还没跟我说就睡着了
He fell asleep before he told me.
等有事我再来 伯纳 你有空了来见我
I'll be back if I'm needed. a word when you're free.
啊 伯纳
Ah, Bernard.
记得提醒我找汉弗莱
Remind me to see Humphrey...
商量...某些事
..about something.
我回来了 是不是有一大堆工作?
I suppose now I'm back, I've got a huge backlog of work?
也不是 首相      不多吗?
Not really. No backlog?
根本没事 首相
Nothing at all.
当首相没什么事做 您已经没有自己的部门了
You have much less to do as Prime Minister.
伯纳 你不是说真的吧
Bernard, you can't be serious.
对 您从报纸上读到的关于首相
Everything you've read about how hard a Prime Minister
日理万机的话都只是传说
has to work is a bit of a myth really.
照例都是新闻部发出去的
It's put out by the Press Office as a matter of course.
不信您自己想想 您有什么要做的?
If you think about it, what do you have to do?
主持内阁      一周两个半小时
Chair the Cabinet. Two and a half hours a week.
主持两个内阁委员会      四个小时
Chair a couple of Cabinet committees. Four hours.
一周接受下院质询两次      又半个小时
Answer questions in the House. Another half an hour.
星期二拜见女王
Er... Audience with the Queen on Tuesdays.
又半个小时      总共一周有七个半小时了
Another hour. Seven and a half hours a week so far.
伯纳 肯定不止这些吧
Bernard, there must be more to it than that.
当然 您得看所有的提要 我们安排您到处握手
You have to read briefs and shaking hands with people.
可除了这些 有很多事人们期待您做
There's lots of things people want you to do
很多事您应该做
and lots of things you should do
还有些您能做 但是很少有事您必须做
and things you CAN do, but very few you HAVE to do.
随您便 您是老大
It's up to you. You're the boss.
谢谢 伯纳 我会考虑的
Thank you, Bernard. I'll bear that in mind.
眼下 叫新闻秘书来讨论我的
Let's have the Press Secretary in to discuss my
第一次首相级电视演讲
first TV broadcast as Prime Minister.
请马尔康华伦马上来一下
Send Malcolm Warren up here straight away, please.
我在美国很忙 极富成效
I was busy in America. It was a great success.
是吗?      当然是的 伯纳
Was it? Of course it was, Bernard.
你没看马尔康的报告吗?
Haven't you read Malcolm's report?
我连着三个晚上在新闻上滚动播出
I was on all the news bulletins three nights running.
"全景"的特写 1,269寸的专栏
Special feature on ''Panorama'', 1,269 column inches
31张照片 16篇广播报道
31 photos, 16 radio reports.
不是 那您取得的成就呢?
No, was it a success in terms of what it achieved?
我刚告诉你了
I just told you.
不 您和美国人的协议怎么样?
No, what about agreements with the Americans?
您和总统的私人会谈 没告诉我结果
Your private conversation with the President?
对了 首先 我给他念了我的摘要
Oh, that. To begin with, I read him my brief
他给我念了他的
and he read me his brief.
然后 我们决定交换摘要自己读 可能会快点
quicker to swapped briefs and read them to ourselves.
剩下大部分时间都在骂法国人
We spent most of the time rubbishing the French.
真好
Terrific.
好
Good. (PHONE RINGS)
喂...? 哦 谢谢
Yes...? Oh, thanks.
马尔康华伦马上上来 首相
Malcolm Warren is on his way up, Prime Minister.
啊 伯纳 我们的首相兼第一财政大臣怎么样?
How's the Prime Minister and First Lord of the Treasury?
正睡得香呢 爵士      伯纳 我们有麻烦了
Sleeping peacefully we have a problem.
谁有?      你 我还有整个白厅
Who has? You and I and the whole of Whitehall.
就是首相要命的新防御观点
The problem is the disastrous new defence ideas -
取消三叉戟 恢复征兵 全是垃圾
cancelling Trident, reintroducing conscription
宏伟蓝图?      对 他就是这么叫的
The Grand Design? That's what he calls it.
如果能省钱 降低失业率...
If it reduces unemployment...
伯纳 我们国防政策的目的是什么?
What is the purpose of our defence policy?
保卫英国      不 伯纳
To defend Britain. No, Bernard.
是为了让人们相信英国受到了保卫
It is to make people BELIEVE Britain is defended.
让俄国人?      不是俄国人 是英国人
The Russians? Not the Russians, the British!
俄国人知道没有
The Russians know it's not.
为了让我们天真 单纯的人民
It's for all our simple, ignorant people
穿梭在家里 巴士和工厂
shuffling in and out of houses, buses, factories
以及内阁的人
and the Cabinet room.
国防是要让他们感到安全
We want to make them feel secure.
但如果有更好的办法...
But if there's a better way...
伯纳 我们有一个魔杖 叫做三叉戟
Bernard, we have a magic wand Trident.
没人了解它 除了它要150亿
Nobody understands it, except it will cost ?5 billion,
就是说它肯定很棒 很神奇
which means it must be wonderful, magical.
我们只须签个支票 就都可以放松了
All we have to do is write a cheque and all relax,
但是 如果政府里的人开始谈论
but if people in government start talking about it,
最后 他们就会开始思考
in the end, they'll start THINKING about it.
最终会意识到有问题 理论中有漏洞
They will come to realise the flaws in the reasoning.
国家就会焦虑 动乱 怀疑 批评 最后改变
The nation will worried agitation, questions...change.
改变?      改变
Change? Change.
还有件事 这次电视讲话
There is one thing, though this TV broadcast.
如果他要宣布他的新政策呢?
Suppose he uses it to announce his new policy?
他不能 要通过内阁和下院
It has to go through Cabinet and the House.
可以的 他可以引起全国大辩论
He can open the national debate.
伯纳 只有政府下定决心以后才可能辩论
You do not until the government has made up its mind.
如果首相打定了主意...      那他得打消
Prime Minister has made up his mind... He must unmake it.
但是他是首相      是 确实是 伯纳
But he's the Prime Minister. Yes, indeed he is, Bernard.
他有公派车 在伦敦有漂亮的房子
He has his own car, a nice house in London,
乡间有别墅 无尽的宣传 终身养老金
endless publicity and a pension for life.
他还想要什么?
What more does he want?
我想他想要管理英国
I think he wants to govern Britain.
阻止他 伯纳
Well, stop him, Bernard.
是要访谈还是要讲话?
Should it be an interview or to camera?
好
Yes.
不 首相 你必须选一个
No, Prime Minister, it has to be one or the other.
访谈怎么样? 伯纳 我们讨论一下电视访谈
What about an interview? we're discussing a TV interview.
要罗宾戴 布赖恩瓦尔登 特里沃根还是吉米杨?
Robin Day, Brian Walden, Terry Wogan, Jimmy Young?
你觉得哪个好?      得看您要什么形象
Which do you think? It depends how you want to appear.
思想家 掌权者 人民的朋友 老好人?
The thinker, man of power, people's friend?
都想 真的      他们四个不可能同时访谈吧
All of them They won't interview you at the same time.
不 是我 我想显示所有这些特质
No, I want to be seen to have all those qualities.
那好 那我想您还是讲话吧
Well, I think you should do it to camera.
好 至少由我负责 不是那些
Yes. At least it'll be me in charge and not
垮台的议员 高傲的主持人
all those failed MPs and jumped-up DJs.
很好 政党宣言?      不 政党宣言会很闷的
Fine. A party political? No, spells instant boredom.
我想应该是一个政府讲话 首相向他的人民演讲
I think it should be a ministerial broadcast
但我要像政党宣言一样冲着镜头
but I'll do it into the camera like a party political.
您似乎说过这很闷      我看他们讲很闷 伯纳
I thought they were boring. I'D be boring, Bernard.
你觉得我讲会闷吗?
Do you think I'd be boring?
闷? 您?
Boring? You?
您常对镜头讲话吗?      不常 主要是访谈
Have you talking to camera? No, mostly interviews.
那我最好安排一个彩排       好
Then I'd better set up a practice session.
还有 这次讲话主要关于什么?
What is the broadcast to be about?
关于什么?      对 是关于什么的?
About? Yes, about. What will it be about?
关于我
About me.
我知道 但是您准备说什么?
Yes, but what are you gonna say?
说什么?
Say?
对 什么政策
About policies.
政策 是 我想就是些一般的东西
Policies, yes. I thought it'd be the usual thing
比如 携手共创美好明天
go forward together, better tomorrow,
勒紧腰带 齐心协力 治愈创伤 之类的
tighten your belt, all pull together, heal the wounds.
是的 但您具体会讲些什么呢?
Yes, but what will you be saying specifically?
哦 具体
Oh, specifically.
我想我会建议我们具体的勒紧腰带
I'd suggest that we all specifically tighten our belts.
具体治愈具体的社会创伤 懂了吗?
And specifically heal the specific wounds in society.
对 完全取决于您 首相
It's entirely up to you, Prime Minister.
我只是在想 您要不要说些新东西?
I just thought if you had anything new to say...?
新东西?
New?
新东西 当然 让汉弗莱再来一下行吗?
Oh, new! of course! Get Humphrey back here, will you?
我的宏伟蓝图 这就是我要跟汉弗莱讲的
My Grand Design. That's what I wanted to talk about.
汉弗莱爵士 首相在安排他的电视讲话
the PM is making arrangements for his TV broadcast.
他想谈他的宏伟蓝图 您能不能...
He wants to talk about his Design and wonders if you...
喂?
Hello?
我想他马上就到
I think he's on his way.
宏伟蓝图?      现在不能告诉你 但是个大工程
Grand Design? I can't tell you now, but it's a big story.
好 首相 我先找个制作人 安排彩排
I'll find a producer, set up a practice in the meantime.
汉弗莱 真快      您想讨论一下电视演讲?
That was quick. You want to discuss a TV appearance?
是的 但也不用这么急
Yes. It's not so desperately urgent.
当然 确实不大重要
Not remotely important.
不重要? 我的第一次首相级电视讲话?
My first television broadcast as Prime Minister?
当然重要 但也没什么大不了的 不用慌
Terribly important, but not a crisis, not a panic.
我想宣布我的新防御政策 你觉得如何?
I want to announce my new defence policy.
不行      什么?
No! Pardon?
这是个错误      你说这政策?
It's a mistake. The policy?
当然 在这个问题上有新想法是很振奋
it's refreshing to have a new mind on the problem.
挑战旧观念 质疑政府30年的思想基础
questioning the basis of government thinking for 30 years.
你不赞成?      不 首相
You don't approve of the policy? It's not that.
会有些牵连 反响 后果
There'll be implications, reverberations, repercussions.
我们需要权衡事实 研究 咨询
We have to weigh the evidence, review, consult.
你继续 汉弗莱 我先宣布了再说
You get on with that I'll announce it in the broadcast.
您不能 现在还不能
You can't. Not yet.
我们得通知美国人 他们会极力反对的
we have to tell the Americans. They will have objections.
需要几个月耐心的外交
It will take many months of patient diplomacy.
微妙问题要小心处理
Delicate issues need sensitive handling.
汉弗莱 英国政府谁说了算?
Who has the last word about the government of Britain?
英国内阁还是美国总统?
The British Cabinet or the American President?
这倒是个有意思的问题
Do you know, that's a fascinating question!
我们常讨论这个      得出什么结论?
We often discuss it. What conclusion have you arrived at?
我是有点异端 我认为是英国内阁 但...
being a heretic I think it's the British Cabinet, but...
我知道我是少数派
I know I'm in the minority.
从现在开始 你是多数派
From now on, you're in the majority.
我要向海外防御委员会提出我的宏伟蓝图
raise my Design with the Overseas Defence Committee,
然后提交内阁
then I shall put it to Cabinet.
我已经私下问过他们大部分了
I've sounded most of them out privately.
他们都说能赢选票...极大提高国防力量
They think it's a vote-winner... a major contribution
我下午提交下院 晚上在电视上宣布
put it to the House, announce it in my broadcast.
抱歉 首相 您现在还不能宣布
Sorry, you can't announce it yet.
如果我不能 谁能?
Well, if I can't, who can?
必须非常清楚地看到
So let us be abundantly clear about this.
我们不能再透支了
We cannot go on paying ourselves more than we earn.
世界上其它国家没有义务赡养我们
The rest of the world does not owe us a living.
我们要准备做出牺牲...谁写的这个垃圾?
We must be prepared to make sacrifices Who wrote this?
您自己 首相 是您以前的演讲
You did, Prime Minister. It's one of your old speeches.
新的呢 电视讲话稿怎么样了?      还在打草稿
The draft of the broadcast? It's still only a draft.
这可是排练      是机密
This is only a practice. It's confidential.
这里都是自己人 拿来      是 首相
Everyone's been cleared. Go on. Yes, Prime Minister.
如何 戈弗雷?      太棒了 首相 只有一点
How was that, Godfrey? Excellent Just one thing.
您要戴眼镜吗?      你觉得呢?
Will you be wearing those glasses? What do you think?
随您 戴上它 您看上去威严而果断
With them on, you look authoritative and commanding.
不戴它 您看上真诚而坦率
With them off, you look honest and open.
我想看上去威严又真诚
I want to look authoritative AND honest.
只能选其一 真的
It's one or the other really.
我可以先不戴 开讲的时候再戴
I could start with them off and put them on when I talk?
这只显得优柔寡断      哦 明白了
That just looks indecisive. Oh, I see.
单片眼镜怎么样?
What about a monocle?
我们先不谈这个行吗? 能再来一遍吗?
Let's just leave them off for the moment Can we go again?
新讲稿拿来了吗? 伯纳      是 首相
Have you got that new script? Yes, Prime Minister.
三叉戟工程耗资太大
The Trident programme is too expensive.
取消它 我们能省下几百万磅
By cancelling it, we shall release billions of pounds
拨款以独特而新颖的方式解决国家问题
to fund an imaginative attack on the nation's problems.
这个国家需要的...      能不能打住
What this country needs... Can we hold it?
怎么了?      没事 很好
What was wrong? No, it was very good.
首相...      等会 伯纳
Prime Minister... Just a minute. Yes?
您能不能不要向前倾?
Do you mind not leaning forward?
这样您看上去像卖保险的
It makes you look as though you're selling insurance.
而且您会向上瞟镜头 像在哀求
it makes you look up at the lens like suppliant.
您应该居高临下
You should be looking down from on high.
好...这个国家需要的 这个国家需要的
What this country needs... What this country needs...
这个国家需要的...
What this country needs...
首相 马尔康和我起草了一份
Prime Minister, Malcolm and I have drafted a
稍稍不同的讲稿      好
slightly different version to this speech.
"我们应广泛考虑政府支出的各种选择"
''We shall review options over government expenditure.''
伯纳 这太空洞了      谢谢 首相
This doesn't say anything. Thank you, Prime Minister.
毫无冲击力      您太客气了
Completely lacking impact. You're too kind.
不 伯纳 我不喜欢      您可以说"紧急考虑"
No, I don't like it. You could say ''urgently review''.
不行      我真觉得应该缓和一点
No. I do think it should be toned down a bit.
怎么缓 马尔康?
Any thoughts, Malcolm?
"三叉戟是你们纳税人的重大负担"?
What about ''the Trident is a burden on your tax bill.
"150亿是一大笔钱 应当谨慎审查它是否值得"
''We should see if it merits the ?5 billion it costs.''
对 提到数字好不好?
All right. It's OK to mention figures?
对 实际上没人记得 记得的也不相信
no one takes them in and those who do don't believe them,
但这能让人觉得您对此了如指掌
but it makes people think you've got the facts.
别忘了 人们不知道您是照提词机念的
People don't know you're reading off the teleprompter.
没别的问题吧?      您念得有点慢了
Otherwise, it was fine? You were going a bit slowly.
提词机走得就慢
The teleprompter was going a bit slowly.
不不 它是跟您的速度走的
No, no. It follows your speed.
试试先慢后快
Try going slow and then fast.
哦 知道了      开始
Oh, I see. And cue.
三叉戟...工程...是...
The...Trident...programme...is...a...heavy...
你们纳税人的负担 150亿是一大笔钱
burden on your tax bill. ?5 billion is a lot of money.
我明白了 真的
I see what you mean, yes.
首相 能不能别说"你们纳税人"?
Would you mind not saying ''YOUR tax bill''?
为什么?
Why not?
听着像统治者在说被统治者 你们我们
It sound like the ruler talking to the ruled them and us.
那我怎么说?      "我们纳税人"?您自己也交税
What should I say? ''OUR tax bill''? You pay taxes, too.
好的 改过来 伯纳
Yes. Change that, Bernard.
是 首相  我还是觉得太直接了
It's still very direct.
谢谢 伯纳      不 很多人靠三叉戟吃饭
Good. No, lots of people's jobs depend on Trident.
如果不经蹉商...      对哦 马尔康?
Until there's been a consultation... Yes. Malcolm?
可以说"国防开支会受政府严格监督"
''Defence is one of areas we will look at closely
"看能不能少花钱来达到同样的防御效果"
''to see if we can meet our needs at a lower cost.''
太长了 能不能分成两句?      怎么?
Can you make it two sentences? Why?
首相 我们发现一句话超过三行
we find that if a sentence goes on over three lines,
等说到最后 多数人都忘了开头了 包括说的人
When it gets to end people will forget how it began.
分两句 马尔康
Two sentences, Malcolm.
而且您又向前倾了
And you are leaning forward again a bit.
我是为了显得真诚
That's what I do when I want to look sincere.
问题是 看上去像您故意想显得真诚
It makes you look like someone who wants to look sincere.
向后倾点 看上去就很放松 很自信
If you lean back, you look relaxed and in control.
就是这样
That's it.
别这么后 那会像您中午喝高了
Don't lean back so far It looks like you've had liquid lunch.
您可以在您想真诚的地方划线
underline bits of the script you want to look sincere,
在那皱皱眉头 说得慢一点
then you just frown and say them a bit more slowly.
还有别的吗?
Anything else?
您的表情有点僵硬
Well, your face is a bit wooden.
僵硬?
Wooden?
对 只有说话的时候才这样
Yeah, only when you're speaking.
一般演讲时 您会动动头 眉毛 面部肌肉等
In normal speech, you move your head and cheek and so on.
别被题词机变成僵尸 好吗? 开始!
Don't let the teleprompter turn you into a zombie.
国防开支
Defence expenditure is one of the areas...
会受到政府严格监督
which this government will be examining closely.
看能不能达到相同的...
It may be that we can achieve the same...
停停 首相 有一点点过火了
Prime Minister, that's just a little bit too much.
你们会听见反对党胡说八道
You'll have heard a lot of nonsense from the opposition.
他们会说我们浪费钱
They say we waste money.
他们会说我们巴结美国
They say we're selling out to the United States.
我说 看看他们当权的后果
I say look at the mess they made when they were in power,
看看他们对经济的破坏
look at the damage they did to the economy...
打住行吗 首相 恕我建议
Could we hold it there? if I might suggest
不要攻击反对党
don't attack the opposition.
党内就爱听这个
Oh. Those are the bits the party likes.
党内横竖会投您的票
Now, the party will vote for you anyway.
您不能让摇摆不定的选民
You'll make the floating voter see you
把您看成愤怒的分裂分子
as an angry and divisive figure.
知道了 那我该怎么说他们?      提都不要提
I see. What should I say? Don't mention them at all.
您所说的一切 都要让您显得热情友好
Everything you say has to make you sound warm
威严 当然 也不失慈爱
Authoritative, of course, but affectionate.
一国之父
The father of the nation.
能不能直接跳到...新东西那里?
Could we just run forward to that, um, that new bit?
尽量降低音调 好吗?
Try lowering the pitch of your voice. All right?
我们要...
(HIGH VOICE) We want...
我们要给子孙后代建设一个美好未来
We want to build a bright future for our children.
要建设一个祥和繁荣的英国
We want to build a peaceful and prosperous Britain,
能昂首世界民族之林的英国
a Britain that can hold head high in the nations.
真不错 谁写的?
This is rather good. Who wrote this?
实际上 是反对党领袖上次的政党宣言
it's the last party political by the opposition.
关于您的形象 您要穿什么?
As for your appearance, what will you wear?
你的建议呢?      深色套装代表传统价值
What do you suggest? dark represents traditional values.
好 深色套装      而浅色套装看上去务实
Fine, dark suit. But a light suit looks business-like.
浅色套装配深色马甲如何?
What about a lightish jacket with a darkish waistcoat?
我觉得会显得您不知自己是谁
that would look as though you've got an identity problem.
抱歉 首相 戈弗雷 能不能谈谈化妆?
Excuse me, PM. could we have a word about make-up?
灰白头发行不行 要染黑吗?      不用 这样很好
Shall we darken the grey hair? No, it's fine.
发际线后移呢?      什么后移?
And the receding hairline? Receding what?
高前额
High forehead.
能不能弄弄眼睛 显得它们不那么贴近?
And can you try to make the eyes less close-set?
好的
Sure.
眼袋打亮一点 脸颊上点色
Lighten the bags underneath.
鼻子还是个问题      问题?
The nose is still a problem. Problem?
不 只是灯光问题 首相 有个大...阴影
No, just a lighting problem. A very large, um, shadow.
牙齿 当然
The teeth, of course.
能不能笑一下 首相?
Could you smile, Prime Minister?
对
Yes...
首相 您想动个牙科手术吗?
how would you feel about a little dental work?
拜托 能再来一遍吗?
Can we get on with this?
好的 再来
OK, we're going again.
太好了 开始 首相
Super. And cue the Prime Minister.
我们应广泛考虑政府支出的各种选择
We shall review options over government expenditure...
伯纳 这是先前那份
Bernard, this is what we started with.
对 我觉得再合适不过了 首相
I do think it's the most appropriate.
你觉得呢 戈弗雷?      这听您的 首相
What do you think? It's up to you, Prime Minister.
我只想说 如果照这么讲
All I can say is, if that's what you're going to say,
我建议穿时髦点 高科技布景
I suggest a very modern suit, hi-tech furniture,
高亮度黄色墙纸 抽象画
high-energy yellow wallpaper, abstract paintings.
全都旨在掩饰讲话本身毫无新意
everything to disguise the absence of new in the speech.
我还是要用我爆炸性的宏伟蓝图演讲
I'll go back to my dynamic speech about the Grand Design.
好 那就用传统布景 深色套装 橡木墙
Fine, then it's the traditional background, dark suit
羊皮卷 18世纪的肖像
leather volumes, 18th-century portraits.
还有 开场音乐
One other thing opening music.
一样 巴赫配创新 斯特拉文斯基配保守
Once again, Bach new ideas; Stravinsky no change.
我想选个英国作曲家 能反映我形象的
I think a British composer, something reflect my image.
艾尔加(浪漫派作曲家)?      艾尔加 好 好
Sir Edward Elgar perhaps? Elgar, yes, yes.
不要 "希望与荣耀之邦"
Not ''Land of Hope and Glory''.
那"神秘变奏曲"如何?
What about the ''Enigma Variations''?
他想说些激进的新东西
He's going to say something new and radical.
又是那个蠢蓝图? 伯纳 明明要你避免的
That silly Grand Design? precisely what you had to avoid!
怎么回事? 给我个好理由
I shall need a very good explanation!
他很热衷      那和这有什么关系?
He's very keen on it. What's that got to do with it?
事情不会因为首相热衷就实现
Things don't happen just because PMs are keen on them.
张伯伦还热衷于和平呢
Neville Chamberlain was very keen on peace!
他觉得能赢选票
He thinks it's a vote-winner.
这就严重了 坐下 他为什么这么想?
That's more serious. What makes him think that?
党派做了民意调查 似乎所有选民
The party did an opinion poll and all the voters
都支持恢复兵役
were in favour of national service.
再做个调查 显示他们反对兵役
Have another poll showing they're AGAINST it
他们不能又支持又反对      当然能
They can't be for AND against it.
伯纳 你被调查过吗?
Ever been surveyed?
我没有 我家房子...哦 我明白了
Yes. Well, not me, my house. Oh, I see what you mean.
伯纳 你知道的 一位可爱的小姐走过来
Bernard, a nice young lady comes up to you.
你当然想留个好印象 不想犯傻 是吗?
You want to create a good impression, do you?
不想      然后她开始提问
No. So she starts asking you some questions.
伍利先生 您担心无业青年增多吗?
are you worried about the young people without jobs?
是的
Yes.
您担心青少年犯罪率上升吗?
Are you worried about rising crime among teenagers?
是的      您觉得学校里缺少纪律吗?
Yes. Do you think our schools lack discipline?
是的
Yes.
您觉得年轻人欢迎权威和领导吗?
Do you think people welcome authority and leadership?
是的      他们喜欢挑战吗?
Yes. They like a challenge?
是的      您支持恢复兵役吗?
Yes. Would you be in favour of national service?
我想应该是      到底是不是?
I suppose I might be. Yes or no?
是      当然 伯纳 你说了前面那些
Yes. After all you've told me
就不可能再说不是
you can't say no.
他们压根不提前面五问 只发表最后一个
They don't mention the first 5 and publish the last one.
他们真是这样吗?
Is that really what they do?
有声誉的调查者不会 不过他们人不多
Not the reputable ones, but there aren't many of those.
或者 这位小姐也能得到相反的结果
the young lady can get the opposite result.
怎么讲?      伍利先生 您担心战争吗?
How? Mr Woolley, are you worried about war?
是的      您担心军备竞赛吗?
Yes. Are you worried about the arms race?
是的      您觉得年轻人持枪学杀人是否危险?
Yes. Is it dangerous giving young people guns?
是的      您不同意强迫人们拿起武器吗?
Yes. Is it wrong to force people to take up arms?
是的      您反对恢复兵役吗?
Yes. Would you oppose national service?
是的
Yes.
看到了吧 伯纳 完美的平衡样本
There you are, Bernard. The perfect balanced sample.
所以 只要自己做个调查
So we just commission our own survey
交给国防部就行了 交给你 伯纳
for the Ministry of Defence. See to it.
好 那电视讲话呢?      他什么时候做?
What about the broadcast? When will he do it?
下个月某天
Some time next month.
告诉他得在...11天内
Tell him it'll be in 11 days' time.
11天? 太快了 要是他拒绝呢?
That's a bit soon. Suppose he refuses?
就说联合广播委员会透露
we've learnt from the Broadcasting Committee
反对党18天后会做政党宣言
the opposition will hold a party political in 18 days
他可以先做电视讲话
and he can get his ministerial in first.
如果他想把任期内第一次政治讲话的
If he wants the first broadcast of his premiership
机会让给反对派 随便
to be given by the opposition, fine.
这是真的吗?
Erm, is that true?
会是的 如果你明早之前不提的话
It will be... if you don't mention it till tomorrow.
他还是可以宣布新政策      我想不会
He could still announce his new policy. I don't think so.
他和内阁同僚只有一次会议机会
He'll have only one meeting with his Cabinet colleagues.
内阁同僚们都支持这个政策
They're all in favour of it.
那只是私下的 政见上的
Only personally and politically
作为各部大臣 他们正式支持吗?
but are they in favour as departmental ministers?
懂了 这取决于他们得到的建议?
I see. That will depend on the advice they get.
当然 我知道 我们从原则上支持他取消三叉戟
there's no question of our opposing cancel Trident.
问题在于 考虑到一切后果之前应该缓行
It's holding back until we've through the implications.
说说 你准备怎么告诉你的就业大臣?
So what are you going to brief your man at Employment?
其他人怎么说?
What are the others saying?
迪克会告诉外交大臣说美国很生气?
Will Dick brief the FS the Americans will hit the roof?
不 他觉得更有力的说法是
No, he thinks it might be more persuasive
取消三叉戟显得软弱 姑息苏联
to argue that cancelling Trident will look like weakness,
好想法
Good thinking.
就像诺曼不会告诉他的国防大臣
Just as Norman won't tell his man at Defence
三军不乐意精锐部队里充斥小流氓
service chiefs won't have elite diluted with riff-raff.
他们是不乐意      他觉得需要别的理由
But they won't? He felt they needed another argument.
两个理由? 这也太压迫国防大臣...
Two? Isn't that putting a strain on the DS's somewhat...
生锈的头脑? 是的
Obsolete intellectual equipment? Yes.
他只会说 三叉戟是最好的
He's just going to brief him that Trident is best
英国得拥有最好的
and Britain must have the best.
好 就算国防部长也该理解这个
Even the Defence Secretary should be able to handle that.
只要稍稍点拨一下 是的
With a bit of coaching, yes.
盖尔呢? 我知道了
And Giles? I know!
教师工会很害怕 征兵会暴露
The Union of Teachers are scared that conscription will expose
毕业生尽管擅长社交和自我表现
that school leavers integrated socially and aware...
却连读写算都不会 对
Can't actually read, write or do sums, yes.
盖尔让教育大臣担心
Giles has got the Education Secretary worried
大学更乐于让军方接收一些学校
that their education is to be taken over by the services
用来教书育人
and actually used for teaching people.
那可不行     不行 你就业部那位呢?
We can't have that. So what about your man at Employment?
一样的
It's the same problem.
说实话 工会无法忍受被小孩抢走社区工作
the unions don't want kids undercutting them on work.
是的
Yes.
我觉得这个阶段用不上事实
I don't think we need to bring the truth at this stage.
等等
Hold on.
假设他说
Now, suppose he argues
眼下的无业青年
that unemployed young people are, at the moment,
不健康 无训练 无组织 无纪律
unfit, unorganised, undisciplined and untrained,
但征兵最终会释放满大街
but that conscription will release on to the streets
健壮 擅长杀戮的青年军人
an army of fit young people, all trained to kill.
说得好
Good man!
他真会相信吗?
Does he actually believe that?
会的 明天早上之前
He will by tomorrow morning.
啊 汉弗莱
Ah, Humphrey.
先生们 借过
Gentlemen. Sorry.
会开得如何 首相?
Good committee, Prime Minister?
奇怪 奇怪      怎么个奇怪法?
Extraordinary. Extraordinary. How extraordinary?
上星期 所有同僚都赞成我的宏伟蓝图
Last week, all my colleagues were for my Grand Design.
现在呢?
And now?
外交大臣说这是向俄国低头
The Foreign Secretary says it would appease the Soviets.
真没想到会这样
I hadn't thought of that.
国防大臣说 三叉戟是最好的
The Defence Secretary says Trident is best
英国就得有最好的
and Britain must have the best.
他真这么说? 真奇怪
Does he really? How fascinating!
教育大臣说征兵会破坏教育系统
The Education says it would undermine the system.
是个问题 就业大臣呢?
It is a worry. And the Employment Secretary?
他说不能把一百万训练有素的
he goes on about a million unemployed trained fighters
失业战士放到大街上
being let loose on the streets.
是有点道理      我就想不通了
Well, he has a point there. I don't understand it.
上星期他们还说 新国防政策
Last week, they all thought my new defence policy
会受欢迎的 你能解释吗 汉弗莱?
was a winner. Can you explain it?
我能力有限 首相 什么 伯纳?
It's beyond me, Prime Minister. Yes, Bernard?
打扰一下 首相 国防部说很紧急
Sorry to interrupt, PM. The MoD said it was urgent.
什么?
What?
好像有74%的群众反对征兵
74% of the population are against conscription.
74...? 天哪
74...? Good Lord!
上次党派的调查说有63%的人支持
The party poll said 63% of the population was for it.
您看 党派的数据很不可靠 首相
party figures can be very unreliable, Prime Minister.
可不是      我提议用折中方案
Evidently. May I suggest a compromise?
显然 委员会认为您的新政策非常好
the committee's agreed that your new policy is excellent
但是基于刚才说到的担心
but in view of some of the doubts expressed,
我认为委员会的意思是 经过再三考虑
may I propose that the view of the committee was
尽管提案纲领得到广泛认可
while the proposal met with broad approval in principle,
某些原则理论原则上可行
some of the principles were fundamental in principle
某些方面太复杂 在实践中需要微妙的平衡
and some of the considerations balanced in practice
所以原则上 明智谨慎的方案
it was proposed that the sensible and prudent practice
只有将提案付诸更加详细的考虑
would be to submit the proposal for consideration,
加强新提案和已有原则的连续性
stressing the continuity of the proposal with principles
以及原则的原则性争论
and the principle of the principal arguments
由提议者在提议中建议批准的 从原则上
which the proposer proposes for approval in principle.
什么?
What?
不要在周五电视讲话上提您的宏伟蓝图
Don't refer to your Grand Design in your broadcast
你不是建议我放弃吧      天哪 不是
You're not suggesting I should abandon it? no!
千万别 这是绝妙的政策
Heaven forbid! It is a most excellent policy!
好吧 我先深入了解一阵再宣布
We'll look into it further before I say anything
首相 电视台要敲定讲话的背景
TV want a decision about the background for broadcast.
还是时髦服装 高科技布景
better be the modern suit with the hi-tech furniture
和高亮黄色墙纸吧
and the yellow wallpaper.
还有抽象画?
And abstract paintings?
得要吧 还有斯特拉文斯基?
I suppose so. And Stravinsky?
是 首相
Yes, Prime Minister.
破烂熊字幕组 -==www.RagBear.com==- 欢迎加入